Indiana University College of Liberal Arts Dean's records, 1909-1915 C189
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University College of Liberal Arts Dean's records
1909-1915
1910-1913
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University. College of Liberal Arts
C189
1.4 cubic feet
During the early years of its existence, aside from a small Law School, Indiana University consisted solely of a College of Liberal Arts (became College of Arts and Sciences in 1921). Horace Hoffman, professor of Greek, served as the first Dean of the College 1894-1920. Collection consists primarily of incoming correspondence from former and proprospectivepective I.U. students. Most of the correspondence consists of inquiries about entrance to the university, transfers, and requests for transcripts or catalogs. The collection is not complete as it ends with the "M" correspondents.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Horace Hoffman was born on 30 July 1855 near Auburn, Indiana. The son of a minister turned farmer, the importance of education was highly regarded by his family. As a result through private instructors Hoffman was prepared for life in an academic setting. After teaching in country schools for five years, Hoffman entered Indiana University in 1877, where he graduated with his A.B. in 1881. For a brief period between 1881 and 1883 Hoffman taught Greek at Indiana University. With the encouragement of President Jordan, Hoffman left the University to pursue a degree from Harvard University where he received his A.M. in 1884.
During Hoffman's service as Dean of the College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, the faculty abolished the grading system, instead choosing to use two criteria for judging student academic performance: "passed" or "not passed". Professor Hoffman, amongst others, was instrumental in attempting to discipline I.U. students who had participated in the "grand bolt" on February 12, 1896, Lincoln's birthday. That year, Washington's birthday happened to fall on a Saturday and many I.U. students felt cheated out of a holiday which would have allowed them a day off from classes. A group of male students decided that on Lincoln's birthday they would skip their classes and try to persuade other students to do so as well. The actions of the rogue students that Wednesday morning soon led to mayhem. A mob gathered outside Kirkwood Hall, indulged in a college-yell, before storming the building and physically removing some students who refused to leave. The mob next stormed the English end of Library Hall and made a second raid of Kirkwood Hall before President Swain and a rain storm drove most of them away. Hoffman and his colleagues made the decision to require all students who were absent from class to write a letter to the Committee of Student Affairs explaining the reason(s) for his or her absence on February 12. Among other events during Hoffman's service as Dean were: the first 'Arbutus' was issued in 1894; William Lowe Bryan was elected university president in June of 1902; Professor Bannister began the publication of the Indiana University Alumni Quarterly; the Student Building was dedicated in 1902; and from 1901 - 1906, Mary Bidwell Breed served as I.U.'s first Dean of Women. Another important event was the creation of the Graduate School in 1904 which relied heavily on the faculty of the College of Liberal Arts and Sciences.
Hoffman was widely respected by his fellow faculty members and is given credit with having helped form Indiana University into the institution that it has become today. Upon his retirement Hoffman was awarded with an honorary LL.D and was named Dean Emeritus of the College of Liberal Arts and Sciences as well as Professor Emeritus of Greek.
Hoffman died on 6 October 1950 in Traverse City, Michigan, at the age of 95.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of incoming correspondence from former and prospective Indiana University students. Many are inquiries about entrance or transfers and requests for transcripts or catalogs. The collection is clearly not complete, as it ends with the "M" correspondents. The fate of the remainder of the correspondence is not known, although it is likely that the later correspondence was interfiled with the President's files.
Arrangement
Organized in single series, Correspondence, arranged alphabetically.
Acquisition Information
Accession 0143
Universities and colleges --Indiana --Bloomington --Administration --History --20th century --Sources.; Deans (Education) --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Deans (Education) --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Indiana University -- Administration -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indiana University. College of Liberal Arts -- Archives; Indiana University. College of Liberal Arts -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. College of Liberal Arts -- History -- Sources; Hoffman, Horace Addison -- Archives; Hoffman, Horace Addison -- Correspondence
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - A (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Grace E, 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Albritton, E.C., 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Aldred, Meredith, 1911-1912 (Box 1)
  - Aldrich, Harry, 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Allen, Ross, 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - Ames, John J., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Anbry, Elizabeth, 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Andrews, Elmer, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, Byron K., 1910-1913 (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, Gabrielle, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, Robert D., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Ashby, Dulcinea, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Ashcraft, Arthur L., 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - Ashman, Katharine, 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - Ba-Bl (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Bailey, C.L., 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - Bair, C.R., 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Baker, Helen, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Baker, T.P, 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, Howard, 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - Bales, Louis, 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - Ballenger, R.E., 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Barnett, Adaline, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Barr, Hugh H., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Bartley, E. Ross, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Baughman, Bernard J., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Baughman, Bessie, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Beal, Chas A., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Bergdoll, Grace, 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Bickwell, Arthur J., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Biddle, Ward Gray, 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Biller, Christine, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Black, Lester, 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Blackburn, William, 1911-1912 (Box 1)
  - Blackhirm, Lura, 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Bm-Bz (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Boggess, Adeline, 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Boshart, E.W, 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Bow, John G., 1910-1913 (Box 1)
  - Boylan, A.L., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Brackenuyere, J.H., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Brandenburg, J. Virgil, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Brauchla, Guy, 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Braudenhug, N.C, 1909-1910 (Box 1)
  - Breituriesen, Thos J., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Briscoe, George A., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Bristol, Samuel, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Agnes Fletcher, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Brown, J.S., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Lucy S., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Mayme, 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Buchanan, J.S., 1911-1914 (Box 1)
  - Butler, E.H., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Butter, Nathaniel, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Butter, O.T., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Butzow, Emma B., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Byrd, Florence, 1911 (Box 1)
  - C (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Cade, W. Roscoe, 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - Cain, M. Jennie, 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Cameron, Angus, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Canon, C.T., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Carlisle, Thos T., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Carner, Chas F., 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Cavanaugh, R.E., 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - Chandler, Jesse, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Chapman, Harold E., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Chrisman, Oscar, 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Christy, Rosa, 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Church, Fredrick G., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Clark, Stella, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Clauser, J.L., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Claxton, P.P., 1913 (Box 1)
  - Clement, Myrtle, 1911-1912 (Box 1)
  - Cline, John H., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Cline, Thurman R., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Coats, Roscoe J., 1913 (Box 1)
  - Cole, M.S., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Connor, William L., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Conger, Maurice B., 1911-1912 (Box 1)
  - Corey, Austin F., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Cortiner, A.J., 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Coucher, Genevieve, 1911-1912 (Box 1)
  - Coyner, A.B, 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Craig, Orville M., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Craig, R.M., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Crosser, Margaret, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Cummings, Helen B., 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Cunningham, R.S., 1911-1912 (Box 1)
  - Curtis, Milo S., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Curtis, W.R., 1911 (Box 1)
  - D (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Daily, Rose, 1911-1912 (Box 1)
  - Daniel, V.E., 1914-1915 (Box 1)
  - Dashiell, Fannie M., 1911-1912 (Box 1)
  - Daus, John, 1911-1914 (Box 1)
  - DeLapp, Albert, 1911-1912 (Box 1)
  - DeLong, John, 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Deal, Veva, 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - Deamer, Arthur, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Deeg, Daniel M., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Deich, John, 1911-1913 (Box 1)
  - Denny, Henry R., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Diamondieff, D., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Dibell, Harry C., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Dilla, Geraldine P., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Dilworth, Homer, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Dix, Floyd, 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Dixon, Gladys, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Dodson, Emily, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Dye, Gretchen, 1911-1912 (Box 1)
  - E-F (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Earle, Frank B., 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Edinger, Lillian, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Edwards, Warren L., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Effinger, John R., 1913 (Box 1)
  - Elliott, Carl L., 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Elliott, Edward, 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Elson, Frank W., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Elwall, J.W., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Emerson, P. Chas, 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - English, Leo V., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Fair, Halcie, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Ford, George W., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Freck, Harry M., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Freley, Wilhelmina, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Furst, Philip C., 1913 (Box 1)
  - G (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Galbreath, Neva, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Geisen, A.H, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Goetcheus, Elizabeth, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Gold, Earl T., 1912 (Box 1)
  - Gordy, Glen A., 1913 (Box 1)
  - Gordou, Walter E., 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Gott, W.T., 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Greene, Evants B., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Greenough, W.S., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Grider, J.F., 1910 (Box 1)
  - Grove, D.A., 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Hj-Hz (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Hogan, Frank M., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Hollingsworth, Berry, 1910-1912 (Box 1)
  - Holloway, J.B., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Hoover, Oliver, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Horshaw, Nellie, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Houk, Glen, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Hovarten, Leroy, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Howard, W.E., 1913 (Box 1)
  - Huffman, Werden D., 1911 (Box 1)
  - Hutchinson, B.O., 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Hyde, Karl C., 1911 (Box 1)
  - I-J-K (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Isenberger, J.C., 1912 (Box 2)
  - Jackson, C.R., 1912 (Box 2)
  - Jaques, Susie, 1911 (Box 2)
  - Jeffrey, Hugh S., 1910-1911 (Box 2)
  - Jenkins, Chas E., 1910 (Box 2)
  - Jolly, W.P., 1910-1913 (Box 2)
  - Johnson, Fannie, 1912-1913 (Box 2)
  - Johnson, J.T., 1910-1911 (Box 2)
  - Jones, C.R, 1912 (Box 2)
  - Jones, George M., 1911 (Box 2)
  - Jones, Ruth, 1913 (Box 2)
  - Kackley, Elizabeth, 1911 (Box 2)
  - Kahin, George S., 1911-1913 (Box 2)
  - Karch, Henry J., 1912 (Box 2)
  - Kellam, Clyde E., 1911 (Box 2)
  - Keuyon, John S., 1911-1912 (Box 2)
  - Kinsey, O.P., 1910-1912 (Box 2)
  - Koons, M.T., 1911 (Box 2)
  - Kyper, K.H., 1912 (Box 2)
  - La-Lz (Box 2)
    - 1909-1910 (Box 2)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 2)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 2)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 2)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 2)
  - Lambert, Francis E., 1910 (Box 2)
  - Lantz, W.E., 1912 (Box 2)
  - Lawrance, Harold G., 1912 (Box 2)
  - Leffel, Sherman, 1912 (Box 2)
  - Leist, Delbert E., 1912 (Box 2)
  - Leonards, Frank, 1911 (Box 2)
  - Lewis, Emily, 1912 (Box 2)
  - Light, Earl S., 1909 (Box 2)
  - Lindermuth, Amy, 1911 (Box 2)
  - Lingeman, Byran, 1912 (Box 2)
  - Linke, J.A., 1911-1912 (Box 2)
  - Loeb, Isidor, 1911 (Box 2)
  - Loveless, A. Pearl, 1909-1911 (Box 2)
  - Ma-Me (Box 2)
    - 1909-1910 (Box 2)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 2)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 2)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 2)
    - 1913-1915 (Box 2)
  - McAdams, C.V., 1912 (Box 2)
  - McCarty, Geo, 1912 (Box 2)
  - McConn, C.M., 1911-1912 (Box 2)
  - McCormack, Chas K., 1909-1910 (Box 2)
  - McKeehan, Charles F., 1909 (Box 2)
  - McNeely, Paul, 1909-1910 (Box 2)
  - Maness, Nan, 1909 (Box 2)
  - Martin, Earl W., 1913 (Box 2)
  - Martin, Theodore T., 1909-1913 (Box 2)
  - Mayne, Walter C., 1909-1912 (Box 2)
  - Merry, Elizabeth Blauche, 1910 (Box 2)